Week sort is one algorithm used to sort a sequence of numbers.
It's part of divide and conquer and good ethics.
So one characteristic of quick sort is that involved that it involves fewer comparisons and scraps than
other algorithms, so it's able to sort quickly in many cases.
Let's take a look at the algorithm in action.
The first operation targets the entire sequence of numbers when a number is chosen as a reference for
sorting.
The number is called that pivot.
So we choose the pivot.
The pivot is normally a number chosen at random, this time for convenience them right.
Most number will be chosen as the pivot.
So six is that pivot and choose that trend.
This is that difficult, a marker will be placed on the pivot for easy reference.
Next, a left marker will be placed on the left mast, no.
And the right marker will be replaced at the right most number.
That quick sword algorithm uses that these markers to repeatedly perform rounds of operation recursively,
so the left marker will move to the right and start by comparing eight.
When the left marker reaches the number, that's greater than or equal to the pivot number.
It stops moving, so it reached number eight.
So AL reaches eight eight is greater than six six.
That that is the pivot.
So it stops then.
In this case, it is greater than or equal to six, so their marker will stop offering that next right
marker will move to the left.
When the right marker reaches a no less than the pivot number, then it stops.
So seven, less than six.
No, it moves for less than six.
Yes.
Then it stops.
So four is less than six.
So the marker stopped moving when both left and right markers have stopped the markers.
Numbers are swapped.
You see guys that we have swept the four and eight.
Then when we have swept them in, there were in this way, the left marker acts to find numbers greater
than or equal to that pivot and the right marker find numbers less than that.
Therefore, by swapping the numbers, the left marker or swapping the numbers, you can gather numbers
that are less than that pivot on the left side of the sequence and numbers that are greater than or
equal to the pivot to the right sequence or to the right side.
After the swab, the left marker continues, moving to the right and start comparing it with the leg
before the left marker moves until it reaches a number greater than or equal to the effort.
So one is less than P. It continues to to do less than be.
Nine is less than we know, it's a greater fact.
So nine is greater than or equal to six, so the marker stop moving.
Now we need to move the right mark.
Once again, the right marker is moved to the left.
The right marker is now movement also stops when the right markers, turns or runs into the left mark.
So left marker and the right marker now meet at the same alma.
When both left and right marchers stopped and they are in the same position.
That number is swept with that pivot.
No, so we have we need to sweep it with the different No.
Again, are no occupied by both the left and the right markers is considered fully sort, this completes
the first round of operation.
The second round of operation with one.
Let me discuss the first round of operation.
We are able to put no smaller than the pivot to the left of the pivot and the numbers larger than the
pivot to the right of the pivot.
Another round of operation will be performed by recursively on both sequences created by the division.
So next operation will be performed on the sequence of the left of the division.
The three markers are placed, these are on there and the left section that we have before the pivot.
So six is the pivot.
We will consider the left section, we will arrange them, we sort through them and we make that quick
short on them and then we move to the right of the pivot.
The three markers are placed, B is chosen by around them, right and left.
They are the most the left, most component and the rightmost component of the pivot.
The same operation as before is performed, left comparing left with pivot.
We move left and right.
The same as before.
So one.
The same operate five is less than two.
So we move, right?
Right and left me now, so.
The same operation as before we we swept the pivot with the left and right indicator.
These are the elements have been swept.
Now the round of operation is complete and we are able to divide the sequence into numbers smaller than
the pivot into the left of the pivot and numbers larger than the pivot to the right of the pivot.
Consider now we have six at the main pivot.
Do as they're left pivot now, the second pivot also now another round of operation is repeated recursively.
The left side of the division will now undergo the operation, so.
We choose here when the target sequence only has one number, it's considered for this sort.
Then there now operation now operations will be performed on the right side, created by the second
round of operations.
The three markers are placed left, right and left.
The left marker will move to the right and they are met.
So even when they were left, marker runs into the right marker, it does not stop.
It differs from the right marker in this respect.
So here is the.
This means that the pivot number is the largest number in that target sequence.
Next, the right marker would be moved, but when it has been passed by the left marker, it finishes
without moving.
When the marker left, where there left marker has reached the right most edge of the target sequence.
The pivot number is considered fully sorted and the round of operations and are here after the same
operation will be repeated until all of their numbers are fully sorted.
Pivot, left and right here, we consider.
All the elements are are fully sorted and here left and right has been blessed by.
Now, this is the single element, we consider it as sort.
Now we move to that part that we have three elements left inside it.
Here, after the same operation will be repeated until all of the elements are fully sorted with Big
B as they aid.
And we have left and right.
These are the leftmost and the rightmost elements.
What a left moves one, because eight is less than nine, so we have moved left and left and are met
at the same position.
Here we go with the left and we go and increase left by one.
And this will indicate for us, right, also would be moving, and this will indicate that nine is the
biggest number inside this sequence.
So a nine would be considered as the greatest between among these elements.
Now we need to sort out eight and seven with Big B as to pivot at seven and al and right will indicate
the eight al will be moved to the two to eight indicate eight.
Now left and right indicate the same position less then or of greater than the pivot.
Then we swab the left and the right by element with the left.
Therefore, we have sorted this.
Now, today, these numbers are being fully sorted using the quick sort.
Maybe it's.
It's sometimes complex for a quick learner or beginner learner or a beginner to understand the quick
sort, but it's very, very easy if you divide the algorithm into many steps and then we start combining
and divide and conquer.
This follows that divide and conquer logic and algorithms.
So I want from you to practice again in that quick sort.
You watched the video and you let us go to that to go deeply in the complexity in the next video and
implement this code and maybe in the coding, you will understand better and better how to implement
this code and how to section this algorithm into many parts and many steps.
So let's move and implement this quick sort into C and.